Guide to the Cornell University Wason Collection records, 1918-1988.
Cornell University Wason Collection records, 1918-1988
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Cornell University Wason Collection records, 1918-1988.
13-6-1721
Cornell University.Library.Wason Collection.
6.4 cubic ft.
Correspondence, articles, clippings, reports, notebooks, and articles.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Mostly department correspondence, largely that of Gussie Esther Gaskill, first curator of the Wason Collection (1927-1963); materials concerning trips to China and Japan; projects; bibliographies; acquisitions, cataloging, and other records; accessions list; accounting statistics, and general office files, 1976-1985; annual reports of the East Asian Librarian, 1972-1988. Correspondence relating to Charles Wason's bequest, especially correspondence between Mrs. Charles Wason and the Arthur H. Clark Company, correspondence between Mrs. Wason and Gussie Gaskill, drawing and photographs of the library at the Wason home, and articles, reports and clippings about the collection. Three handwritten notebooks by T.F. Crane listing the Wason Collection, ca. 1922.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
The Wason Collection was bequeathed to Cornell University in 1918 by Charles William Wason. It began as a collection of English-language works on China and the Chinese. Its scope and size have since been greatly enlarged, and it is now the only major East Asian collection in the country to include all Western language materials in the areas covered in a special collection together with the materials in the languages of those areas.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Mostly department correspondence, largely that of Gussie Esther Gaskill, first curator of the Wason Collection (1927-1963); materials concerning trips to China and Japan; projects; bibliographies; acquisitions, cataloging, and other records; accessions list; accounting statistics, and general office files, 1976-1985; annual reports of the East Asian Librarian, 1972-1988. Correspondence relating to Charles Wason's bequest, especially correspondence between Mrs. Charles Wason and the Arthur H. Clark Company, correspondence between Mrs. Wason and Gussie Gaskill, drawing and photographs of the library at the Wason home, and articles, reports and clippings about the collection. Three handwritten notebooks by T.F. Crane listing the Wason Collection, ca. 1922.
Miscellaneous items relating to the Wason Collection include letters, description, and notes about the Ming Treasure Note, 1934; and letter about and translation of a Boxer Rebellion poster, 1921.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Cornell University.; Crane, Thomas Frederick, 1844-1927.; Gaskill, Gussie Esther, 1898-; Wason, Charles William, 1854-1918.; Wason, Charles William, Mrs.; Cornell University--Library.
Subjects:
Libraries--Special collections--Chinese literature.; Librarians.; Women librarians.
Places:
China.; Japan.; East Asia.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Boxes 2, 3, and 4 (accession of 9-28-83) are restricted to permission of office of origin.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Records related to Miss Gaskill's curatorship
  - General correspondence, filed alphabetically by the name of the correspondent
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous papers
    - Miss Gaskill and the Far Eastern Bibliography, 1946-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Miss Gaskill and Far Eastern libraries (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Miss Gaskill and the ALA-CCS Special Committee on Far Eastern Materials, 1953-1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Miss Gaskill and Cornell University (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Miss Gaskill and Wason Collection Chinese book orders (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Miss Gaskill and Japanese book orders (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II. Wason material sent to Archives
  - AAS Annual Meeting 1980 (Box 2)
  - AAS Convention (Box 2)
  - Acquisitions ( 1965-1976) (Box 2)
  - Asian Studies Department (Box 2)
  - Bibliography (Society for the Humanities) (SH 391) (Box 2)
  - CALRFE (Box 2)
  - Cataloging Far Eastern Materials (1959 and 1964) (Box 2)
  - CEAL (Box 2)
  - China travel - brochures (Box 2)
  - China trip 1979 (Box 2)
  - China, Japan, and Taiwan trip 1980 (Box 2)
  - China trip - CEAL report (Box 2)
  - Collaborative Studies of China and Japan Newsletter (Box 2)
  - CUL Bulletins (Box 2)
  - East Asian Libraries projects (Box 2)
  - Heydecker ( 1974-1976) (Box 2)
  - LC information 1978 (Box 2)
  - Library information - directors, etc. (1970, 1973-1974, 1978-1979) (Box 2)
  - Luce Foundation (Box 2)
  - Maryland (University Library) (Gordon Prange - 1979) (Box 2)
  - Missing books - list (1972-1975, 1980) (Box 2)
  - Newsletters (CUL) ( 1977-1980) (Box 2)
  - Newspaper orders (Box 2)
  - OAKS ( 1978) (Box 2)
  - Wason - Bibliographies (1959-1966) (Box 2)
  - Wason - gift exchange acknowledgments (1963-1976) (Box 2)
  - Wason - Exhibit: "China and the West" (1966); "Asia and the West" ( 1974) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence ( 1963-1980) (Box 3)
  - Memoranda ( 1961-1963, 1967-1980) (Box 3)
  - Additions to shelves, 1979 (Box 4)
  - Accessions lists ( 1979-1980) (Box 4)
  - Chinese Collection - reports, memos, etc. (1962-1979) (Box 4)
  - Department heads and designated assistants meeting notes ( 1978-1980) (Box 4)
  - Reports from the Director (1968-1980) (Box 4)
  - Reports on various subjects (1970-1971, 1977) (Box 4)
  - Support Staff Advisory Committee notes (1978-1980) (Box 4)
  - Wason Accessions List, Jan. 1981-June 1985 (Box 5)
  - Wason Additions to Shelves, Jan. 1982-June 1985 (Box 5)
  - Title II-C, 1979-1983 (Box 5)
  - Accounting statistics, July 1981-June 1985 (Box 5)
  - AACR2 ( 1979) (Box 6)
  - Annex titles (Box 6)
  - Annual Report (Asian Studies, 1979-1980) (Box 6)
  - Annual Report (Directors, 1978-1979, 1981-1982) (Box 6)
  - Annual Report (Gift & Exchange, 1980-1981) (Box 6)
  - Annual Report (Wason, 1979-1980, 1980-1981, 1981-1982, 1982-1983) (Box 6)
  - Automation ( 1979-1981) (Box 6)
  - Chinese names (Box 6)
  - Correspondence outside Cornell (1981-1984) (Box 6)
  - Development ( 1979-1981) (Box 6)
  - East Asian Librarian (1979-1981) (Box 6)
  - Employment inquiries (1979-1981) (Box 6)
  - Equipment/maintenance (1981) (Box 6)
  - Figures and Fundraising (1979-1980) (Box 6)
  - Gift & Exchange (1980-1981) (Box 6)
  - Japan Foundation ( 1979-1980) (Box 6)
  - Japanese Series (Box 6)
  - Journals ( 1980-1981) (Box 6)
  - Library Committee (Box 6)
  - Mellon Grant (Box 6)
  - Memos received ( 1981) (Box 6)
  - Memos sent ( 1981) (Box 6)
  - Memos (Acquisition, Gift & Exchange), 1982) (Box 6)
  - Memos (Administration, 1981-1982) (Box 6)
  - Memos (Catalog Dept., 1982-1983) (Box 6)
  - Memos (China & Japan Program, 1982-1983) (Box 6)
  - Memos (Circulation, Public Service, 1982) (Box 6)
  - Memos (Mr. Finch, Mr. Oey) (Box 6)
  - Memos (Graduate School - Alison Casarett, 1982) (Box 6)
  - Memos (Mann Library, 1983) (Box 6)
  - Memos (MMN, 1983) (Box 6)
  - Memos (Serials, Binding, 1982-1983) (Box 6)
  - Memos (Outside Library, Cornell U., 1981-1983) (Box 6)
  - Missing books (1982-1983) (Box 6)
  - National Union Catalog (Box 6)
  - National Repository for Chinese Agriculture Publications (Box 6)
  - Pinyin (Box 6)
  - Principles of Managing (1979) (Box 6)
  - Printing (Box 6)
  - Security ( 1979) (Box 6)
  - Selection ( 1979-1981) (Box 6)
  - Serials cancellations (1981) (Box 6)
  - Serials currently received (1979-1981) (Box 6)
  - Statistics reports ( 1979-1982) (Box 6)
  - Syllabi (Box 6)
  - U.S. corporations in China and Japan (1980) (Box 6)
  - Wason budget and fund (1982) (Box 6)
  - Wason selection policy (1977-1981) (Box 6)
  - Wason statistics ( 1981-1982) (Box 6)
  - Xerox word processing (Box 6)
  - Wason staff (Box 6)
  - Annual reports of the East Asian Librarian, 1972-1988 (Box 7)
  - Wason miscellany including correspondence about Boxer Rebellion poster; correspondence, etc. about Ming currency; articles from Pacific Affairs (2 folders); "Translation of Euclid's Elements" (Box 7)
  - Correspondence relating to Wason bequest, 1918-1920 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with Mrs. Wason (mainly Gussie Gaskill), 1921-1949 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence about the Collection, 1942-1975 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Library Reports (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Reports and articles (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Clippings (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Desciption of Wason's library (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Photographs of Wason's library (Box 8, Folder 8-11)
  - Chinese dragon flag from Mrs. Wason (Box 8)
  - Note cards (Box 8)
  - Three handwritten notebooks by T.F. Crane listing the Wason Collection, ca. 1922 (Box 9)
  - RMC China related (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified tables (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Kumming Hu Album (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Wason - Warhol, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Ship logs transcriptions (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Hu stuff (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Groom, other subjects in Chinese (Box 10, Folder 7)